<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lachrimæ lachrimarum. or The distillation of teares shede for the vntymely death of the incomparable prince Panaretus. by Iosuah Syluester</title>
            <author>Sylvester, Josuah, 1563-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118065</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853274</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853274</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18644</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13274)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18644)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1293:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lachrimæ lachrimarum. or The distillation of teares shede for the vntymely death of the incomparable prince Panaretus. by Iosuah Syluester</title>
                  <author>Sylvester, Josuah, 1563-1618.</author>
                  <author>Quin, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Humfrey Lownes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Panaretus = Prince Henry Frederick.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Includes poems in English, French, Latin, and Italian by Walter Quin.</note>
                  <note>Title is xylographic (white-line).</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon, which is printed in a border of woodcuts on D4r. Sheets A and B are often mixed with other editions, or may exist in reimpositions which have not yet been adequately studied.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Text printed on rectos only; versos are mourning pages.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry Frederick, --  Prince of Wales, 1594-1612 --  Death and burial --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <add>C23576 Sylvester, Joshua</add>
            </head>
            <p>
               <add>Sylvester (Joshua) Lachrimae Lachrimarum, on the Distillation of Teares shede for the untymely death of the incomparable Prince Panaretus, FIRST EDITION, <hi>calf extra</hi> 
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1612 ORIGINAL AND MOST RARE EDITION, and not to be confounded with the comparatively common reprint of 1613, when it was accompanied by other productions. The <hi>only other</hi> copy of the present <hi>editio princeps</hi> which has occurred during the last forty years is that in the Huth library. (See Collier's "Rarest Books in the English Language," 1865, ii. 410-11, for some account of Sylvester.) The volume is curiously printed on one side of the leaves, the reverse being in black with the royal arms gartered and crowned in white relief at the top, and the printed pages having at head and foot a mourning band, with emblems of mortality at the sides. Sylvester's poem ends on B4; on C1 begins, and continues to the end, a series of verses on the same subject in English, French, Latin, and Italian, by Walter Quin of Dublin, who is styled the Prince's servant.</add>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add>First Edition.</add>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:3"/>
            <figure>
               <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LACHRIMAE LACHRIMARVM. or</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Distillation of Teares <hi>Shede For the vntymely Death of</hi> The incomparable Prince <hi>PANARETVS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>by Iosuah Sylueſter.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:4"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:4"/>
               <head>LACHRIMAE LACHRIMARVM. A funerall <hi>Elegie</hi> vpon the All-<hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented Death of the</hi> All-admired <hi>(late) PRINCE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>How-euer, ſhort of Others <hi>Art and Witt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I knowe my powers for ſuch a Part vnfitt;</l>
                  <l>And ſhall but light my Candle in the <hi>Sunne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To doe a Work ſhalbe ſo better <hi>Donne:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Could <hi>Teares</hi> and <hi>Feares</hi> giue my Diſtractions leaue,</l>
                  <l>Of ſobbing words a <hi>Sable Webbe</hi> to weaue;</l>
                  <l>Could <hi>Sorrowes Fulnes</hi> giue my voice a vent,</l>
                  <l>How would! how ſhould my ſaddeſt <hi>Verſe</hi> lament</l>
                  <l>(In deepeſt Sighes, inſtead of ſweetest Songs)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This Loſſe</hi> (alas!) which vnto All belongs:</l>
                  <l>To all the Godly <hi>now,</hi> and <hi>future,</hi> farr:</l>
                  <l>To all the <hi>WORLD</hi> (except <hi>S P. Q. R.</hi>):</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:5"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:5"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>To All together, and to Each a-part</l>
                  <l>That liues, and loues <hi>Religion, Armes, or Art:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To all abroad, but to vs moſt of all</l>
                  <l>That neerest ſtood to my <hi>High Cedars</hi> fall:</l>
                  <l>But more then moſt, to <hi>Mee,</hi> that had no <hi>Prop</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But HENRY's <hi>Hand,</hi> and but in <hi>Him,</hi> no <hi>Hope.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Deereſt HENRY; <hi>Heav'n and Earths Delight!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O cleereſt <hi>Beame</hi> of <hi>Vertues,</hi> Riſing bright!</l>
                  <l>O pureſt Spark of <hi>Pious</hi> Princely <hi>Zeale!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O ſureſt Ark of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> ſacred weale!</l>
                  <l>O graueſt Preſage of a <hi>Prudent</hi> kinde!</l>
                  <l>O brauest Meſſage of a <hi>Valiant</hi> Mynde</l>
                  <l>O All-admird, <hi>Benign</hi> and <hi>Bountious!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O All-deſired (right) PANARETVS!</l>
                  <l>(PANARETVS <hi>(All-vertuous)</hi> was thy Name</l>
                  <l>Thy Nature ſuch: ſuch euer bee thy Fame).</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O deereſt! cleereſt! pureſt! ſureſt <hi>Prop!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O grauest! braveſt! Highest! nigheſt <hi>Hope!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O how vntymelie is this Sunne gonne downe!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This</hi> Spark put out, This <hi>Ark</hi> (as) ouerthrowne!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:6"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:6"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Preſage croſt! This Meſſage loſt and left!</l>
                  <l>This Prop diſplac't! This Hope of All, bereft!</l>
                  <l>O! How vnkinde! How, graceleſſe! How, ingrate!</l>
                  <l>Haue <hi>Wee</hi> cutt-off Thy likely longer Date!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, were <hi>This Stroak</hi> from Heav'ns immediat hand;</l>
                  <l>Or (by Heav'ns leaue) from Hells ſuborned Band:</l>
                  <l>How c'r it were, <hi>Wee</hi> were the <hi>Mouing Cauſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That ſweet <hi>Prince</hi> HENRY breath no longer drawes.</l>
                  <l>Wee All (alas) haue had our hands herein:</l>
                  <l>And Each of vs hath by ſome <hi>cord</hi> of <hi>Sinne</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hal'd downe from Heaven, from <hi>Iuſtice</hi> awfull Seat</l>
                  <l>This Heauie <hi>Iudgement</hi> (which yet more doth <hi>Threat</hi>)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wee Clergie</hi> firſt, who too too oft haue ſtood</l>
                  <l>More for the Church-goods then the Churches good:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wee Nobles</hi> next, whoſe Title, euer ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>Can hardly offer Right, or ſuffer Wrong:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wee Magiſtrates,</hi> who moſtly, weake of ſight,</l>
                  <l>Are rather faine to feele then ſee the Right:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wee Gentles</hi> then, who rack and ſack, and ſell,</l>
                  <l>To ſwimme like <hi>Sea-Crabs,</hi> in a <hi>foure-wheeld Shell:</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:7"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:7"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wee Courtiers</hi> next, who <hi>French-Italianate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faſhion</hi> our <hi>Faith</hi> after the forme of <hi>State:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wee Lawyers</hi> then, who in the forme of <hi>Law,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Diſ-claiming <hi>Conſcience</hi> like the Horſe-leach drawe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wee Cittizens,</hi> who ſeeming <hi>Pure</hi> and Plaine,</l>
                  <l>Beguile our Brother, make our <hi>God</hi> our <hi>Gaine:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wee Countrey-men,</hi> who ſlander Heav'n and Earth</l>
                  <l>As Authors of Our <hi>Artificiall Dearth:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>All, briefly All; all Ages, Sexes, Sorts,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Countries, Citties, Benches, Churches, Courts,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(All <hi>Epicures, Witt-Wantons, Atheiſts,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mach'-Aretines, Momes, Tap-To-Bacchoniſts,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bats, Harpies, Sirens, Centanres, Bib-all, nights,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sice-ſinckap Aſſes, Hags Hermaphrodites)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Wee,</hi> poore <hi>Nothings</hi> (fixed in no Spheare,</l>
                  <l>Right <hi>Wandring</hi> Tapers, <hi>Erring</hi> euery-where)</l>
                  <l>Scorne of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> ſcandall of the <hi>Gowne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Haue pull'd this Waight of <hi>Wrath,</hi> This <hi>Vengeance</hi> down:</l>
                  <l>All, All are <hi>guiltie,</hi> in a high Degree,</l>
                  <l>Of This <hi>High Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracie,</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:8"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:8"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>More brute then <hi>Brutus,</hi> ſtabbing <hi>more</hi> then CAESAR,</l>
                  <l>With Two-hand-SINNES of <hi>Profit</hi> and of <hi>Pleaſure.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, for the <hi>Peoples</hi> Sinnes, for <hi>Subiects</hi> crymes,</l>
                  <l>God takes-away good <hi>Princes</hi> oftentymes:</l>
                  <l>So good IOSIAH (HENRY's <hi>parallel</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Was (yong) bereft from Sinfull <hi>Izrael:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So our good EDWARD (HENRY's <hi>Pre-cedent</hi>)</l>
                  <l>For ENGLAND's <hi>Sinnes</hi> was hence vntimely hent.</l>
                  <l>So heer, good HENRY is newe taken hence,</l>
                  <l>For now <hi>Great</hi>-BRITAN'S great <hi>Sinnes</hi> Confluence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wee ſee th' Effect, wee haue the Cauſe confeſt:</l>
                  <l>O! <hi>Turne</hi> wee then, with ſpeed, to <hi>Saue the reſt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O! Turne vs, <hi>Lord;</hi> turne to vs, turne away</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Frownes,</hi> our <hi>Feares,</hi> with humbleſt Teares wee <hi>pray.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O! ſaue our <hi>Souverain;</hi> ſave his <hi>Royall ſeed;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That ſtill his <hi>Owne</hi> may on his <hi>Throne</hi> ſucceed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let Each of vs make <hi>priuie Search</hi> within;</l>
                  <l>And hauing found, bring forth the <hi>Traitor</hi> SINNE</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Execution,</hi> with all <hi>Execration</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Henceforth renouncing ſuch <hi>In-Sin-newation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:9"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:9"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let Each of vs (as Each hath thrown a <hi>Dart,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Dart</hi> of Synne, at HENRY<hi>'s</hi> princely hart)</l>
                  <l>Send-vp in Sighes our <hi>Soules</hi> devouteſt breath,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Shield</hi> our IAMES, ANNE, CHARLES, ELIZA'BETH</l>
                  <l>And HIM, whoſe <hi>Loue</hi> ſhall render HER her <hi>Brother,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And make Her ſoone a happie <hi>Princes</hi> Mother.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let Each of vs ceaſe to lament (in vain)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prince</hi> HENRY<hi>'s Loſſe.</hi> Death is to HIM a Gaine</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Sauoy's</hi> Dukelings, or the <hi>Florentine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He</hi> Wedds his <hi>Sauiour</hi> (of a Regal <hi>Ligne</hi>)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Glorie,</hi> for <hi>Gold;</hi> for <hi>Hope, Poſſesſion (there)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of Crownes</hi> ſo Rich as neuer entred Eare,</l>
                  <l>Eye neuer ſawe, nor euer Hart conceav'd;</l>
                  <l>So strong <hi>Aſſur'd,</hi> as cannot be bereav'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Waile not his death: His <hi>Vertues</hi> cannot <hi>Dye</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Immortall Iſſue of ETERNITIE)</l>
                  <l>His Soule in Bliſſe beholds her Makers Eyes:</l>
                  <l>His goodlie Body ſhall more glorious <hi>Riſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Weepe</hi> not for HIM: weepe for our ſelues (alas)</l>
                  <l>(Not for our <hi>Priuate,</hi> or <hi>Peculiar</hi> caſe:</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:10"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:10"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>As for our <hi>Sonn's, Brother's,</hi> or <hi>Maſter's</hi> lack,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Prince's</hi> loſſe (our <hi>Expectations</hi> wrack)</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Places, Graces, Profits, Penſions</hi> lost,</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>preſent Fortunes</hi> caſt, our <hi>future</hi> croſt)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Weepe for our <hi>Sinnes,</hi> our <hi>Wicked</hi>-Prouocations,</l>
                  <l>Our haynous, horrid, high ABHOMINATIONS,</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>ſeen</hi> and <hi>ſecret;</hi> both in High and Lowe:</l>
                  <l>Weep, weep for <hi>Theis;</hi> and ſtript from Top to Toe,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>guiddie-Gaudes,</hi> Top-gallant <hi>Tires</hi> and <hi>Towers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Face-pride, Caſe-pride, Shin-pride, Shoo-pride, ours</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(<hi>Like</hi> NINIVITES, ſo neer Their <hi>threatned Fall</hi>)</l>
                  <l>In blackeſt <hi>Sack</hi> and <hi>Cinders</hi> ſhrowded All,</l>
                  <l>With bended Knees, but more with broken harts,</l>
                  <l>And th'<hi>inward</hi> reſt of right <hi>Repentant</hi> Parts,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Proſtrate</hi> our Soules in <hi>Faſting</hi> and in <hi>Praier,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Before the Foot-ſtool of th'<hi>Empyreal</hi> CHAIRE:</l>
                  <l>That So, What-euer bloodie <hi>Deluge</hi> float</l>
                  <l>From th'old <hi>Red Dragons</hi> wide-wide-yawning <hi>Throat,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wee, Humbled</hi> MOVRNERS, may be Heau'nly <hi>Markt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In MERCIE's <hi>Veſſell</hi> to be All imb <hi>Arkt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaphs">
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:11"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:11"/>
               <head>THE PRINCES EPITAPH, WRITTEN BY HIS HIGHN. <hi>ſeruant,</hi> WALTER QVIN.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>O here intomb'd a peereleſs Prince doth lie,</l>
                  <l>In flowre &amp; ſtrength of age ſurpris'd by death,</l>
                  <l>On who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, while he on earth drew vitall breath,</l>
                  <l>The hope of many Kingdoms did relie;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not without cauſe: for heauens moſt liberally</l>
                  <l>To him all Princely vertues did bequeath,</l>
                  <l>Which to the worthieſt Princes here beneath</l>
                  <l>Before had been allotted ſeuerally.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But when the world of all his vertues rare</l>
                  <l>The wiſhed fruit to gather did expect,</l>
                  <l>And that he ſhould ſuch <hi>glorious workes</hi> effect,</l>
                  <l>As with the worthieſt fame might him compare:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vntimely death then from vs did him take;</l>
                  <l>Our loſſe, and griefe, heauens gaine, and ioy to make.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:12"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:12"/>
               <head>Idem in obitum eiuſdem Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſsimi Principis.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>OCcidit ante diem iuuenum flos, gloria ſtirpis</l>
                  <l>Regalis, Patriae ſpes, columen<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuae.</l>
                  <l>Occidit ante diem, patri populiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Britannis</l>
                  <l>Flendus, &amp; his iunctis foedere, amore, ſacris.</l>
                  <l>Occidit ante diem, gesturus Principe digna,</l>
                  <l>Acceleraſſet ei ni fera Parca necem.</l>
                  <l>Occidit ante diem, virtutis &amp; vbere fructu,</l>
                  <l>Et mundum exemplo funere deſtituens.</l>
                  <l>Occidit ante diem, ſi vota &amp; commoda ſpectes</l>
                  <l>Publica, vel vitam ſi breuitate notes.</l>
                  <l>Sin vitam ſpectes partam illi morte perennem,</l>
                  <l>Haud iam, par Superis, occidit ante diem.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="fre" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:13"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:13"/>
               <head>Stances du meſme Anthour ſur <hi>le meſme ſujet.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>TAnt plus qu'vn bien eſt grand, &amp; rare en excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</l>
                  <l>Et que la iouiſſance en a plus de plaiſir;</l>
                  <l>Tant plus auſsi la perte en a de deſplaiſir,</l>
                  <l>Et ſe fait regretter auec impatience.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ceci ſe monſtre aſſez en la fruition,</l>
                  <l>Qu'auons eu d'vn grand Prince, en tous biens admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable;</l>
                  <l>Et en ſa triſte mort, d'autant plus deplorable,</l>
                  <l>Que rare de tout point fut ſa perfection.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tant l'eurent la Nature, &amp; la vertu enſemble,</l>
                  <l>Et la fortune auſsi de leurs dons enrichj,</l>
                  <l>Que de quelle des trois il fut le plus cherj,</l>
                  <l>De pouuoir bien iuger malaisè il me ſemble.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>De l'eſtoc plus ancien d'entre les Roys extrait,</l>
                  <l>Il fut ſi bien douè des dons de la Nature</l>
                  <l>En corps, &amp; en eſprit, que iamais creature</l>
                  <l>N'a eſtè de ſon Art chef d'aeuure plus parfait.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:14"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:14"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>D' elle il eut la beautè, la grace, &amp; bienſeance,</l>
                  <l>Force, addreſſe, eſprit vif, &amp; inuincible caeur,</l>
                  <l>Grandeur &amp; Maieſtè meſlee auec douceur,</l>
                  <l>Que reluire on voioit voire en ſa contenance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>La vertu ſe voyant par Nature appreſtè</l>
                  <l>Vn ſi riche ſujet, l'enrichit dauantage</l>
                  <l>En le rendant pieux, temperè, preux, &amp; ſage,</l>
                  <l>Iuſte, clement, &amp; plein de largeſſe &amp; bontè.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ceſte meſme vertu luy feit les Arts apprendre,</l>
                  <l>Par leſquelz vn grand Prince a bien regir en paix,</l>
                  <l>Et a bien ſouſtenir de la guetre le faix;</l>
                  <l>Quand il en eſt beſoing, capable se peut rendre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>La fortune enuers luy fauorable auſsi fut</l>
                  <l>Sur ſes plus chers mignons luy donnant l'auuantage:</l>
                  <l>Car threſors &amp; grandeurs &amp; le riche heritage</l>
                  <l>De maint païs &amp; Roiaume, &amp; mainte ville il eut.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Il ſembloit que ces trois auec telle largeſſe</l>
                  <l>L'ayans de tous leurs dons a l'enui eſtrenè,</l>
                  <l>Parla faueur du Ciol il fut au monde nè,</l>
                  <l>Pour viure vn ſiecle entier en gloire, heur, &amp; lieſſe;</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:15"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:15"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Et pour faire jouir aux ſiens l'exemple &amp; fruit</l>
                  <l>Dos ſes faits vertueux &amp; en paix, &amp; en guerre;</l>
                  <l>Et eſtendre ſon loz aux bornes de la terre,</l>
                  <l>Ou noſtre hyuer eſté, noſtre jour ſe fait nuit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O que le monde auoit bien beſoin de ſa vie?</l>
                  <l>Car il ſeruoit d'eſpec, &amp; bouclier aux amis;</l>
                  <l>De terreur, &amp; de fleau contre les ennemis;</l>
                  <l>De rempart aſſeurè, &amp; d'ancre a ſa Patrie;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>D'appui, &amp; de defence a ſon Pere Royal;</l>
                  <l>A ſa Mere d'honneur; de miroir a ſon frere;</l>
                  <l>D'ornement a ſa ſaeur; aux Princes d'exemplaire;</l>
                  <l>De merueille, &amp; de ioye a tout peuple loial.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mais, helas, ce grand Prince en la fleur de ſon age,</l>
                  <l>Et de noſtre eſperance (O triſte coup du Ciel)</l>
                  <l>Nous a eſté rauí: dont en fiel noſtre miel</l>
                  <l>Se change, &amp; noſtre ioye en dueil, regret, &amp; rage.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Ciel a quelle fin nous preſtás tu ce bien,</l>
                  <l>Ce joyau non-pareil, ce miroir de Nobleſſe,</l>
                  <l>Pour nous l'oſter ſi toſt? he que ce coup nous bleſſe,</l>
                  <l>Nous foudroie, &amp; fracaſſe, &amp; reduit preſqu'en rien?</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:16"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:16"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>A quelle fin ie voj: c' eſt pour prendre vengeance</l>
                  <l>De noz meſchancetez, &amp; horrible meffaits,</l>
                  <l>Que ſi cruellement tu deſcoches tes traits</l>
                  <l>Sur nous pauures chetife, &amp; miſerable engeance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Trop bon pour nous il fut: reprendre il t'aura pleu</l>
                  <l>Ton cher gage, duquel auons ioui nagueres,</l>
                  <l>Affin d'en embellir tes plus belles lumieres,</l>
                  <l>Et de le reunir a ſon celeſte feu.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mais enuers toy, cher Prince, ô quel deuoir nous reſte?</l>
                  <l>Auec toy nous faut il nous eſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouir du ſoit,</l>
                  <l>Qui t'eſt eſcheu au Ciel, des bienheureux le port?</l>
                  <l>Ou regretter ta mort aux tiens par trop funeſte?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>L'un, &amp; l'autre ferons: t'applaudiril conuient</l>
                  <l>En ce que tu jouas ſi bien ton roole au monde,</l>
                  <l>Et la viens a reuiure ou tout bonheur abonde,</l>
                  <l>Et ou tout dueil en joye a conuertir ſe vient.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mais tant pius que nons fut ta vie douce &amp; chere,</l>
                  <l>Et qu'en fleur d'ans la mort nous te vint arracher;</l>
                  <l>Les reſnes d'autant plus nous conuient il lacher</l>
                  <l>Au dueil, en regrettant noſtre perte, &amp; miſere.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="ita" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:17"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:18644:17"/>
               <head>De. medeſimo ſopra il <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſimo Suggetto SONETTO.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>IL fior' de Prencipi nel fior' de gl'anni,</l>
                  <l>Et delle noſtre ſperanze, ora è colto</l>
                  <l>Della ſpietata morte (ahi laſſo) e tolto</l>
                  <l>A noi dol n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ì e miſeri Britanni.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A neſſun' popol' mai diè tanti affanni</l>
                  <l>Morendo alcun' gran Prencipe, per molto</l>
                  <l>Ch' <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i foſſe amato quanti il nostro ſciolto</l>
                  <l>Dal corpo cì laſcia e dolarì, e danni.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dal Ciel pareu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ch' cì c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> foſſe dato,</l>
                  <l>Pe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>che del Padr é ſucceſſor nel Regno</l>
                  <l>Foſſe, eſelio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, e chi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro e'n pace, e'n guerra.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ma cì vien tolto (ohime) dal Ciel irato</l>
                  <l>A danni noſtrì per che diſedegno</l>
                  <l>Stimollo, e indegna eſſer' dì luì la terro</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:18"/>
            <trailer type="illustration">
               <figure>
                  <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>gartered and crowned English royal blazon</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:18"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>memento mori border</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>H D</head>
                  <q xml:lang="lat">OS HOMINI SVBLIME DEDIT</q>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Humfrey Lownes.</hi> 1612.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:19"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q xml:lang="ger">ICH DIEN</q>
                  <figDesc>printer's device: coronet of the Prince of Wales adorned with three ostrich feathers</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:20"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18644:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
